so last week talked we talked about
feelings laying them rise on their own
and I guess weird time they persists and
then they go not leaning towards the the
pressure of wanting told that more of it
hmm wanting less of whatever feeling has
arisen hmm
and I've been reflecting on that
sometime and I trying to stop my old
tendency of like feeling feeling or how
am I feeling and sort of like those old
mindfulness tendencies are sort of
reflexively labeling the painting to
myself what's going on I guess what came
to my mind was there's a determination
that arises from feeling like to want
more of it if it is pleasing or to not
want it if it's not pleasing and the
determination if it's a neutral feeling
is I guess most a time is sort of like
it persists for a time as they go
alright this is this is a neutral mood
gratitude but then there's sort of like
anxiety that builds up hmm and a
restlessness yeah and then wanting to
seek some kind of experience or stimulus
I was thinking to myself and in line
with reading a suit involving the Buddha
told my thinking and pondering or jhanas
or even Brahma viharas these abodes of
thinking and thought in that way it's
sort of seeking a pleasure of Pleasant
abiding as it said in the Super's and
the word says it's a it's a blameless
thing to
seek out and and have it at the same
time that is a desire to want well no
that's the thing the those Pleasant
abiding is not something you can want
which means in order to get the Pleasant
abiding of jhana first you need to stop
running away from unpleasant the
bindings that are not jhana in other
words you can't use jhana to replace the
unpleasant abiding stead for you
restlessness anxiety and so on that's
why in every whenever the Buddha
describes the jhana he would say that
worry and concern about the world have
been abandoned beforehand he has been
living with draw from sensuality
beforehand he experienced pleasure on
account of it and then he minds and his
monitors jhana so you can't want jhana I
mean you can want it in a theoretical
sense like all is something were
developing it but developing jhana
cannot be rooted in your desire which is
why it's blameless so when the Buddha
talks about the pleasure of jonah it's
it's the basically it's the pleasure of
you not needing to run away from pain
anymore that becomes pleasant because it's a
that becomes pleasant because it's a
relief because you're not bothered by
the pain and that's how you want jhana
you don't enter Jannah by replacing the
the feeling of discomfort or anxiety
whatever else with this great pleasure
that is blameless that is sensuality
basically that's exactly oh sure it is
that's where people turn to sensuality
when they are you know bit down or
something bothers there let me scratch
my itch and experience pleasure and
forget about things that bother me and
yes exactly that's why people meditate
with their sensuality more often they're
not
so you can its it you wouldn't be able
to achieve jhana
through I guess finding disagreeable
feelings or unpleasant feelings just
trying to replace it and like in that
sounds like oh right now I'm
experiencing some sort of unpleasant
mood or at it
so let me as I say like think thinking
and pondering upon a certain duh
as I say meta or Karuna yeah you want to
see why you're doing that see why
because yeah exactly
oh I'm thinking pondering upon meeting
Karuna because I want to get rid of this
discomfort and that's why you won't be
getting a little bit discomfort
correctly you're trying to replace it
you're trying to do the practice but
still doing the practice is secondary to
you first wanting to be free from pain
but the practice is basically not giving
in on account of how you feel not giving
in to the actions of it so that I mean
that practice becomes your action of
dealing with pain and because of that
you won't be looting that pain so one
pain rises to just let persist well let
it persist
obviously you will the thoughts will
have to be there of some kind so even if
it's the thoughts that are hoping that
the pain will disappear as long as you
don't lose perspective on those thoughts
you won't be giving in to that hope you
will be practicing indifference
regardless so so hoping that the pain
disappear will be seen as part of the
pain not part of what you wanted what
you feel entitled to so directing I mean
the entirety your mind is just directed
only on feeling and violate I guess
being attentive to that feeling of
rising not trying to direct it elsewhere
or directed know again see what why
would it be a problem
you could directed elsewhere why is that
a problem as I can see sort of
mean thoughts I mean as restlessness why
do you rather why do you need to stay
with the feeling hmm why do you must not
allow your thoughts to go elsewhere
because then I'll become distracted by
my thoughts and then I'll start thinking
either something pointed towards
sensuality just ravaging myself through
my thoughts with sensuality of what I
could be getting and forgetting that I'm
even feeling so and then why would you
not want to be distracted from
sensuality distracted by yeah so yeah
why would you want to avoid that because
that would be me trying to find her I
mean that's will be my normal tendency
of buying an escape right sure sure but
I'm not asking why would you you that
that's the reason why you would go to
sensuality to find escape so why are you
not now not wanting to go to sensuality
because you don't want to find escape
because I want to develop knowledge and
understanding in regards to Dharma and
become free from that from what the
craving that sort of tendency or impulse
to move away from and why would you want
to be free from debt
it leads to at least to thinking in
regards to on Olson thoughts into pain
basically it leads to further pain and
down the line in a future so so leads to
further pain does that mean it's totally
painful suppose it would because it's
like an agitated it is so that's one cuz
you want to not experience pain mmm-hmm
so you would go to sexuality with
previous habits because you don't wanna
experience pain now you're restraining
sensuality for the same reason because
you don't want to experience pain either
way you're affected by the pain so you
want to recognize then that and that's
why I see that's why sensitive strain
cannot automatically result in freedom
from pain but that's where sensory
strain is a necessary basis for the
result of being free from pain but that
result will never occur for as long as
your minder stays on the level of what
you're doing as in I'm doing sensuality
what I'm doing restraint of sensuality
so the restraint of from sensuality is
necessary but in itself it's still the
same action rooted in the same reason of
trying to avoid pain so that's why just
restrained in itself you need to
maintain but if there is no wisdom
sensuality is still kind of the value so
to speak so now you're just saying no to
it which is a necessary step but in
itself cannot lead you to the result
that you want and the result that you
want is when you start recognizing that
through sense restraint being
established beforehand you start
recognizing that ah doesn't matter what
you even like this sense of duty I must
practice Dhamma for this for this for
the future prevention of pain all of
that is secondary to the fact that right
now right here you have experience of
discomfort against which you crave to
not be and that's the root of all of
your pains future pains past pains not
what actually happened to
you so see even like sensuality is not a
direct cause of pain that's why it's
it's it's hard to approach it because
you don't necessarily see the connection
but sensuality is direct cause of
craving proliferation of craving and
then once you start equating craving and
suffering than you realize yet
sensuality is the cause of suffering
right here right now not not even in the
future as you said you're already
pressure and agitated by the pressure of
that direction and that's already
unpleasant which means pain is already
there why cause craving is already there
so you don't want to prevent pain from
coming your way because you can't but
you can certainly prevent maintenance of
craving for which you're responsible and
you're responsible by giving in to pain
or giving in to pleasure by taking
things up you maintain the craving love
it
so that so it's always important to keep
the context as to why not all because of
this let's see you would explain you
know because the future suffering
because of this because of this but if
you keep pushing it it's always gonna
come back to here and now because it
cannot be anywhere else you can't
experience suffering today on account of
craving from yesterday you can
experience craving today on account of
which you suffer today and yes that
craving has been maintained yesterday
and day before yesterday before
yesterday but your suffering is not ever
because of previous cravings it's only
because of the present craving that's
why it's felt presently or you cannot
experience you cannot feel the feeling
of any kind in the past and you cannot
feel the feeling of any kind in the
future can only be felt presently it can
be on account of future things sure but
it's felt presently it can be on account
of past actions past things that happen
to you but it's felt presently so that's
what I mean you cannot prevent the
feeling from occurring because it's not
within your domain of control you were
subjected to it and then in the same
sense you don't need to I must stay
mindful this in a sense of I must be
just looking at this feeling because
whether you look at it or not it's felt
they're so really you need to learn how
to feel it without needing to stare at
it all the time is this forgetfulness
that occurs being aware of it okay so
this is my move this is my attitude
currently but then things are do
restlessness occurs and the thoughts
just like story yeah and that's on the
problem that's part of the anxiety it's
you losing the sight of the whole
picture on account of what's happening
that's how you lose your recollecting
this not because of what type of
thoughts are there so if you have
thoughts of restlessness and anxiety you
included within the situation part of
the situation it's I guess extremely
damning in that sense just it's like a
tie like just a flood just like sort of
Sri Lanka wherever I am there see even
that is not a silly problem you don't
need to constantly tell yourself that
you're in the Kuti or in Sri Lanka your
situation then easier is those thoughts
but you include that as secondary to the
feeling not something I must do must
prevent Lisa must remove this now it's
just part of the experience that's gotta
mean during and that's the whole point
seeing that experience comes and goes on
its own and you are subjected to it it's
not other way around which means you
can't choose what you're subjected to it
yeah certainly not directly you can
choose to not be subjected to sensuality
by leading the life of restraint by
avoiding the central environment and so
on but that's only like kind of
circumstantial level of control which is
all you can do that's why you have to
develop these things beforehand as the
Buddha would say but yes so that's right
like in the inside the perimeter he
knows the mind effectively lost his mind
effectively lost mind affected with
restlessness has mind effectively
restlessness as in it's not you must
deal with this you must prevent it you
must tackle it no it's the mind affected
by this thinking like this don't lose
perspective on it that's the extent of
your responsibility now that this must
stop occurring that is you overshooting
the mark which is why you
mein affected by it so during these
moments of restlessness and constant
thinking when don't try to get rid of it
and don't give in to it how you do that
you do that by when you want to get rid
of it you don't or when you want to give
in it you don't I wanna tell you oh do
this to do that because then there will
become like your output for trying to
get rid of it so if I said what perhaps
you could see what what is your body
doing while you're restless you might
see that accurately first but then
looking at what my body is doing while
I'm Restless will be what you do in
order to get rid of the restlessness and
you don't want that but yes in a way
included in your situation but your body
still needs to be there even if you
completely overwhelmed by the thoughts
in your mind it's still in the count of
the body present enduring in a seated
position is Esther it's the pressure of
the tendons you wanted to get rid of the
pain that's always the problem that's
always why you would lose perspective so
you need to start training in regard to
that not giving in to the pressure to
get rid of the pain which means you need
to learn how to endure it on that dry
level and sometimes you lose the sight
sometimes you want if the precepts are
established beforehand you won't act out
of it in extremely unwholesome manner
then everything else can be contained
and then you can start seeing through
that eventually recollecting like after
these states yeah you need to recollect
that you mustn't try to get rid of it
you like that's basically the root of
your recollection because that's the
root of your motivation now what exactly
you recollect through the recollection
of I mustn't get rid of this that's
secondary that's why you can have any
reference point doesn't need to be
specific one but if I tell you I'll
recollect the body you will be unaware
that the motivation behind you
recollecting your body is trying to get
rid of the pain
which is the same motivation as why you
would give to sensuality in the past
which is the motivation that perpetuates
the craving in regard to how you feel
and that's how it's not freeing you
that's why psychology and psychotherapy
is important when it comes to actually
uprooting the problem can only manage it
so you want to recognize that now this
is unpleasant means I want to get rid of
it recognize that context cultivate that
context and that's how you stop trying
to get rid of it when you stop trying to
get rid of it you stop craving against
it
absence of craving means absence of
suffering that's when you get to the
standard anxiety was not unpleasant
things were not unpleasant it was your
own craving in regard to things that was
unpleasant
I guess most of my life I mean since
I've read the sutras
since I began monastic life and living
at monastery I took it on myself to read
a super removal of distracting thoughts
and I sort of followed that as a method
like you know if this thoughts is going
to lead down you know into the
unwholesome then it's better to I mean
they had the four different yeah methods
the steps you know either just recognize
it for what it is yeah and then go on
its own or substituted try the opposite
Russian mind anymore and yeah you know
try to stop it and I guess I still have
that sort of same sort of tendency of
being like okay so this you know it's
bad and I must you know nobody's even
that should substitute the toltmanns
first understanding what they are and
that's the problem of people it's that
sort of gentleman which he doesn't
tolerate thoughts of ill-will or
thoughts of sensuality means I must get
rid know you tolerating it or not is a
new a rising of the thing is not on you
yet when you read not tolerate you think
I must get rid of its presence as a
simile I was given before like somebody
comes at your doorstep you let them in
or you don't that's a new if they if you
if you close the door they can stand it
as long as
there that's not a problem that's will
say he doesn't welcome the thoughts of
sensuality he doesn't delight in it
he doesn't entertain it and that's how
you get rid of it the person will leave
your doorstep when he realizes he's not
coming in by the way he will not be
allowed in he gives up and that's saying
the matter you know he's still assails
and attacks but like the light and mind
he dealers are I'm wasting my time here
and then the model leaves then you stop
having even those assailing thoughts but
not understanding that like to what
extent is your responsibility that's how
you think I must go out and chase it
either way you get involved either way
that person sees that he has effect on
you whether you let them in or shout
them you acknowledge them and that's the
point that's all they want
mara wants acknowledgement/recognition
so recollecting the context recollecting
the like being aware of the content in
order to recollect the context not
trying to get rid of the content is the
context you want to cultivate in the
context yeah knowing in terms of just
seeing what's there not in terms of
analyzing or figuring it out that's
irrelevant to who's pushing it away so
it's not even in my view exactly not
trying to deny the content and
network my own that's seeing the content
recollecting of the context that
increases my understanding and so well
increases increases familiarity now with
that relationship and everything else
that you know from sutras will can be
well you can begin seeing it against
that new familiarity ah see I used to
read this she doesn't tolerate the
sensual thought yes
that can mean I'm gonna try and get rid
of it but it can also mean I don't
tolerate it for whatever it has a reason
I don't entertain it I don't say yes
come please no so I'm not welcoming it
I'm not entertaining it I'm not
delighted when I can't of it so then you
realize the things you thought you
understood can be understood in even in
a different manner in a greater manner
so this week in a more accurate manner
because now are you developing the new
context you become familiar with content
in context of the content content is
what you can attend to directly context
is the peripheral of it all this
okay the context of this is I don't want
it I want to get rid of it I'm gonna act
out of it I want it to disappear that's
the context of your action but it is
that context is contradictory because I
even didn't have seen this arising yet
Here I am hoping I can remove it and
that's why you suffer you don't suffer
because of the arising of the thing you
suffered because you're claiming towards
it yeah yeah that is steady stands true
on that kind of circumstantial level
then there's the more subtle kinds of
yeah look you don't become a sort of
by gradually removing your proteges and
suffering you become a solar panel like
what the suitors say by AB rooting the
thorn of suffering and then as a result
of that all of your other suffering will
fade because you remove the root the
source of it and that's the important
thing to understand because otherwise
you think that all these little
circumstantial practices you do are
somehow magically contributing to this
suffering diminishing it's our way
around first you need to understand what
suffering is and by doing so you fully
approved the call of it then all the
other residues will fade away but not
like through fading away of the residues
I will deplete the core that's why again
the photo overshoots is what makes a
solar panel there is suffering as in
suffering is there I understand it I
understand what it is I understand what
what causes it what is the reason for
suffering so which means until the soda
party you don't even know what suffering
it and that's exactly the case but
Regina thinks suffering is in the eyes
in the sights in the sound smell taste
touches and so on suffering is in what
such-and-such said to you suffering is
in not getting this then you secondarily
remove your desire so you don't want
things in the future so you don't get
disappointed so you don't suffer that is
as I said circumstantially correct and
yeah it's still better than being
heedless completely but you're not
uprooting the suffering suffering was
never in getting what you want or not
getting what you want suffering was
always rooted in presence of craving in
regard to presence of feeling and that's
what you need to understand if you
understand that all the other suffering
will be depleted sometimes sooner
sometimes later but it will have to be
depleted
understanding craving in regards to fuel
yeah so first you need to recognize what
feeling is then stop trying to get rid
of it
stop trying to go towards it stop trying
to go away from it so trying to ignore
it by practicing that you're practicing
attitudes that are not compatible with
craving and that's how craving
diminishes I think about like eating a
meal sometimes we get varying kinds of
food sometimes sugar content those lines
so understanding as I'm eating the
content of the food and this is sweet
this is you know tasty you know this is
gonna give me make me I guess give me
more pleasant feelings of eating or
something but understand that that
context like I mean not rejecting the
food no you can't exist and the same you
know you can try and avoid the taste and
always eat what you don't want to eat
thinking that's how sometimes somehow
you will avoid the craving but you want
you're already acting out of that
craving you just recognize that you
cannot remain indifferent towards taste
so you're trying to hide it now you need
to develop a greater context than the
context of taste you need to develop a
greater reason for eating then the
reason of taste and then just keep mind
on that level doesn't matter how much
you enjoy it or not the food so what is
the greater context well as the Buddha
said you reflect you ponder you keep in
your mind even when you don't eat the
reason why you would eat it's just to
stay healthy to have enough strength to
enjoy elements and so you can practice
the Dhamma and you eat only to the point
of diminishing the hunger or to
overeating so keep that context while
you're eating enjoyment or non enjoyment
become secondary
so it's the most agreeable food you can
have but you are only keeping your mind
on am I still full or am I not full you
feel full fine
stop eating doesn't matter what else is
left to be eaten
you don't feel full stop worrying about
how tasty the food is because that's not
the reason religion once you stop
worrying about it
what am I am I start doubting it you
lost the context of the right the
reasons for eating the hindrance without
hindrance of worry and did you
obstructive you and now you see by
worrying about the taste you give power
to the taste trying to get rid of the
taste you give power to the taste by
indulging the taste carelessly you give
power to the taste by not worrying about
any of those movements but maintaining
the context of mindfulness the reason
for eating is removing hunger the moment
hungers gone you stop eating that's it
you remain true to the right principle
your mindfulness remain undiminished
even if it doesn't feel right
there doesn't matter how you feel it's
not supposed to feel right it's not
always gonna feel pleasantly coz yeah
when the hindrance is present he's gonna
torment you but that's the point you're
not acting anymore
from how you feel you're acting from the
right context and that's the point
hindrances don't disappear even in jhana
you disappear from the domain of
hindrances but they remain living where
they were because all hindrances are
bodily they're bound with the body
that's why the buna they're felt there's
always discomfort and everything else
even doubt and restlessness your mind is
bound with the body in the same sense so
you don't overcome hindrances by
preventing them from arising you
overcome interest is by being
imperturbable regardless of their
arising or not that's how you are not
hindered by that
this comes from not acting out of
feeling and always understand the
context not like always I must always
understand it's simply not losing it
like understanding of the context
doesn't require attentive maintenance
just requires clarity of understanding
that's it so it becomes effortless I
mean he is he always thinking about his
nose I send the only one who reviews if
knowledge or something prompted he's not
obsessing and that's also how our hand
still has preferences I prefer to this
over this this is more agreeable this is
less agreeable none of that is rooted in
desire and craving anymore but if you
refuse to ever look beyond the
Preferences beyond the pleasure that you
get through eating you refuse to look at
the common different any different
context and sometimes people refuse to
look that way because they're afraid
they're afraid that if I look away from
i must avoid pleasurable tastes then i
will automatically go back to
pleasurable tastes but that's not the
case you go back to pleasure taste when
you choose to go back to pleasure taste
but you remain bound with the dependence
and pleasurable taste for as long as
you're trying to deny the pleasure
ability of the things so they think that
through denying they can replace the
dependence on pleasurable tastes and
because of that they don't so only
through discerning the greater context
regardless of pleasurable at this
pleasurable taste you get this amount
the dependence on the taste the danger
yeah it's like there's enough for
different things you would understand
this is one thing that gets fully
understood in all these facets
yeah whenever he uses that kind of
formula to describe means full
understanding like full complete clarity
in regard to that context where no need
or method to recollect the danger well
you'll be you won't be see you you will
need to recollect the danger because you
haven't fully understood which means you
haven't fully understood the danger so
yeah you should be trying to understand
the danger of course but don't think
that that's what the Buddha means by
this formula he fully understands it so
for you you need to fully understand
your dependence on it your freedom from
it and you're fully free means you fully
understood the danger the scared the
gratification you